<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The common catechisme with a commentary therevpon, by questions and answers, following the verie words, as they lie in their order without alteration. A profitable way, as also verie easie, and so likewise pleasant both to the teacher and learner, as by experience will be found true. By Richard Bernard, pastor at Batcomb.</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08997)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1195:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The common catechisme with a commentary therevpon, by questions and answers, following the verie words, as they lie in their order without alteration. A profitable way, as also verie easie, and so likewise pleasant both to the teacher and learner, as by experience will be found true. By Richard Bernard, pastor at Batcomb.</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Sta[nsby] for Samuel Man, at the Swanne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COMMON Catechiſme, With a Commentarie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, by Queſtions and Anſwers, <hi>following the verie words, as</hi> they lie in their order without alteration.</p>
            <p>A profitable way, as alſo verie ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſie, and ſo likwiſe pleaſant both to</hi> The Teacher and Learner, as by experience will be found true.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD BERNARD, <hi>Paſtor at Batcomb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Sta.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Man,</hi> at the Swanne in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull, M. <hi>Thomas Hanham</hi> Eſquire, to the wel-affected Gentle-woman his Wife, and to their whole family, found knowledge, with increaſe of faith, which worketh by loue, is heartily wiſhed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had made an eſſay in your Family, of this manner of Catechiſing, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you ſo well to approue thereof, as to deſire a written Coppie to inſtruct your Houſhold, I promiſed it: but for that ſome other haue alſo requeſted the like of mee, I thought it fit (being thereto alſo intreated) to publiſh it for the greater benefit.</p>
            <p>This is eaſily learned of any that can ſay the words of the common Catechiſme, ſo much neglected. This bindeth the Learner ſtrictly to the words of that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, in anſwering to the Queſtions here propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: And ſerues more to direct the Maſter of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to make queſtions out of that Catechiſme, then for other to learne to make anſwere thereunto, if they, can but ſay the words, except in ſome few places.</p>
            <p>This manner of queſtioning to draw anſwers from the words as they lie in order, may bee obſerued not onely in Catechiſmes, but alſo in reading holy Scrp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as is not vnknowne to my people here at home, with good fruit.</p>
            <p>This my labour ſuch as it is for the preſent, I preſent you with. For I acknowledge your good fauour towards
<pb facs="tcp:19882:3"/> my ſonne, and I am very thankfull in his behalfe, as he alſo himſelf is, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r ready vpon any occaſion to expreſſe it to your ſelfe, as alſo to that worthy honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Knight, Sir. <hi>Walter Earle,</hi> at whoſe requeſt it pleaſed you ſo fauourably and freely to beſtow the liuing.</p>
            <p>I cannot but make mention of him, when I write of Catechiſing to you, for his more then ordinary religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care in the well trayning vp of his family this way. In all my dayes, among all my acquaintance I haue not ſeene the like: and I rather admire it, when I conſider his daily imployment ſundry waies otherwiſe in publik buſineſſes, the leaſt wherof doth commonly draw moſt men from almoſt alea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of inſtructing their houſholds. But what cannot a ſetled reſolution, an induſtrous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a holy zeale, and a godly care to haue religion in honour, make a pious and deuoted heart to doe.</p>
            <p>Sir, I pray you accept this vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aigned witneſſe of my thankfulneſſe, and a ſome little furtherance for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of your familie, vpon which I heartily wiſh a bleſſing from God the Author of all good; to whoſe gracious guidance, I commend you and all yours, and ſo in all due reſpectfulneſſe I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips, to be commanded. Rich: Bernard,</signed> 
               <dateline>Batcomb.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE <hi>To the Reader.</hi> By Queſtion and Anſwer vpon the <hi>Title of the Booke, and the parts thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> HOw many things are you to obſerue for entrance into this Booke?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The title and the book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is the title?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>CATECHISME, <hi>that</hi>
               </hi> is An inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be learned of euery Child, before he be brought to be confirmed by the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> What things are you to conſider in this title?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe fiue circumſtances. 1. The name of the Booke, a <hi>Catechiſme.</hi> 2. The expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the name, an <hi>inſtruction.</hi> 3. Why it was ſet out, <hi>to be learned.</hi> 4. Of whom, <hi>of Children.</hi> 5. When and in what ſpare of time, <hi>before they come to be confirmed by the Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is there any difference betweene this Catechiſme and other Catechiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not in ſubſtance, nor in manner of deliuery, but in other reſpects,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. In reſpect of the <hi>Generalitie</hi> of it for all places. 2. Of the publike <hi>Athority</hi> commanding it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is a Catechiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is an <hi>Inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is euery inſtruction a Catechiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but an inſtruction of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, by the way of Queſtion and, Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In how many things then doth a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme differ from other inſtructions?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In two things. 1. In the matter, the principles of Religion. 2. In the manner, by queſtion and anſwer,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it ſet forth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That it may be both taught &amp; leraned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How is that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two wayes; according to his Maieſties directions, ſet forth to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be thoſe two waies?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. By examination, in propounding the Queſtions and receiuing the Anſwers. 2. By expoſition, in giuing the ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words, for further benefit to all the hearers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is a Catechiſme to be learne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For many reaſons. 1. For better ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of mens iudgements in the truth, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well grounded in the principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. 2. To profit the more in reading holy Scriptures 3. To heare Sermons with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and iudgement. 4. To diſcouer error. 5. To be able to examie our ſelues of our faith, of our duties to God and man, of our right deuotion in prayer, and of the holy vſe of the bleſſed Sacrament, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to receiue. 6. To be able readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue an anſwer of our hope to any one. 7. To be able to teach and admoniſh others, eſpecially ſuch ouer whom we haue a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Catechiſme to bee taught and learned before all other Catechiſmes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. To ſhew obedience to authority, commanding this euery where to be taught. 2. For vniformity ſake, that the ſame truths from on and the ſame Catechiſme, may bée knowne to all in euery place. 3. For the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of ſuch as remoue their dwellings from one Pariſh to another, that Children and Seruants may not be to ſpéee in their anſwers, when they come to be catechiſed, as it otherwiſe falleth out by variety of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſmes taught in ſeuerall pariſhes,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Q.</hi> Who is to learne this Catechiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Euery Childe comming to yeeres of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many wayes is the name <hi>Childe</hi> to be taken?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two waies, according to the Scrptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. For a Childe in yéeres, as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vnderſtood. 2. For a Childe in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding as the ſcripture ſpeaketh. 1. <hi>Cor. 3. 1. Heb.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Whom comprehend you vnder the name of Children in yeeres?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All Children, Apprentiſes and ſeruants, which haue not learned this Catechiſme,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How muſt theſe be taught?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By examination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Who are to be vnderſtood by Children in vnderſtanding?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ignorant of the grounds of Chriſtian faith, though married and well ſtrucken in yéeres, yea, the very eldeſt for age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How are theſe to be catechiſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By their being preſent with attention, when others are examined, and by hearing their Teacher expound the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> When and in what ſpace is this to bee learned?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19882:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Before any either be admited to receiue the Lords Supper, or be brought vnto the Biſhop to be confirmed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it to be learned before any come to the Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by the knowledge hereof they may be the better prepared thereunto, without which preparation they are not counted ſit to be communicants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it to be learned before one bee brought to the Biſhop?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That hée may now in his owne perſon make profeſſion of his faith, and with his owne mouth ratifie that which in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was by his God-fathers and God-mothers promiſed in his name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But ſeeing our Church doth not allow Confirmation for a Sacrament, nor doth acknowledge that it addeth any thing vnto Baptiſme, why are Children brought to bee confirmed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. To ſée whether Children haue béen ſo religiouſly trained vp, as their God-fathers and God-mothers promiſed, and vowed at Baptiſme for them. 2. Whether they be able to promiſe and profeſſe ſo much now in their owne perſons. 3. Hauing ſo done, that prayer may bee made vnto God, for his bleſſing and grace to ſtrengthen them,
<pb facs="tcp:19882:6"/> that they may continue and increaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vnto their liues end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> HAuing gone through the <hi>Title</hi> now can you tell me how many parts the Booke conſiſts of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of theſe two. 1. Of the Preface. 2. Of the matter of the Booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the Preface?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All that which goeth before the rehearſall of the Creede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Preface containe in it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The foure firſt queſtions, with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is the matter of the Booke, or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the Créed, the tenne Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Lords Prayer, &amp; the Doctrine of the Sacrments.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <head>The Common Catechiſme.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>The firſt Queſtion.</head>
               <p>Q. WHat is your name?</p>
               <p>A. N. or M.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many names haue you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, a Chriſtian and ſurname.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What may they put you in minde of?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of a twofold parentage, naturall and ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who are your naturall Parents?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My Father and my Mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who are your ſpirituall Parents?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God and his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which of theſe two names are demanded of you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My Chriſtian name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And why ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That by this name I may be put in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of my Baptiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>The ſecond Queſtion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> WHo gaue you this name?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When was that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In my Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What were you made in it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A member of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What hath a member relation vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To a body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many bodies hath he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two: a naturall, as we haue, &amp; a myſticall.<note place="margin">Eph. 5. Col. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:7"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of which are you a member?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of his myſticall body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What body is that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is he to his Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He onely is the head thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth he then vnto it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hee giueth it ſpirituall life, motion and direction as a head doth to the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What muſt you feele in you, to be ſure that you are a true member of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That I doe liue by him to God, am mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by his ſpirit, and directed by his word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Being thus a member of Chriſt, what doth this make you to be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Child of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> How commeth this to paſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the grace of adoption,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And being thus Gods Childe, what then are you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am made <hi>an Inheritour,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To haue then the hope of heauen, what muſt you firſt be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſure of heauen be the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, and the true Childe of God elſe ſhall I not inherit that Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:7"/>
               <head>The third Queſtion.</head>
               <p>WHat did your God-fathers and God-mothers then for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They did promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kinde of promiſe was it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>A vow</hi>
                  </hi> vnto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many things did they promiſe and vow?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In whoſe name?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In my name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt of theſe three?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That I ſhould forſake all the Enemies of my ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe thrée, the Deuill, the World, and the Fleſh,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the <hi>Deuill</hi> named firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe hée was the firſt authour of all ſinne and euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When doe you forſake him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When I forſake <hi>all his workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the <hi>World</hi> put in the ſecond place betweene the Deuill and the Fleſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Deuill doth vſe it common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a meanes to intice the fleſh to ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by the World?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The pomps and vanities <hi>thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What make theſe this World to be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>wicked worid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When doe you know, when you forſake the World?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When I doe forſake all the pompes and vanities thereof, and not before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the fleſh named in the laſt place?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is within vs, and leaueth vs not vtterly till the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> What meane you by the <hi>fleſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The luſts <hi>thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What luſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the ſinfull <hi>luſts of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When doe you then know, that you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fleſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When I doe forſake all the ſinfull luſts therof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why did your ſureties promiſes for you, that you ſhould forſake them, when you weare but newly borne?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe from the wombe wée are Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to Satan, ſlaues to the world, and ſeruants to the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When can we then forſake them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Neuer, except we be borne a new of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the ſecond thing, which they promiſed and vowed for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That I ſhould beleeue.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the Articles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What Articles meane you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Articles of my chriſtian faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the third thing they promiſed and vowed for your?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That I ſhould keepe God holy will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When keepe you this his will?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When I keepe <hi>his commandements.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King 34 &amp;. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;. 8. 58. Luke 1. Deut. 5</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And when keepe you them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When <hi>I walke in the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How long muſt you do ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the dayes of my life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>The forth Queſtion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> DOe you thinke that you are bound to beleeue, and to doe, as they haue promiſed for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes verily.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But by whoſe helpe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By Gods helpe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You muſt then doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And ſo I will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> With what minde towards God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As heartily thanking our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he hath called me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To the ſtate of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Through whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What is he to vs herein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now being in this ſo happy eſtate, what is your daily exerciſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I pray vnto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To giue me his grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What to doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That I may continue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the ſame ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How long?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto my liues end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of the Creede.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> CAn you rehearſe the Articles of your Beliefe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, I beléeue in God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, maker of heauen and earth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What make you confeſſion of in this Creede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <hi>I doe beleeue.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is his attribute?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Almigihty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why call you him ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For that he is the <hi>maker of heauen &amp; earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In whom elſe beleeue you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is he to God the Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His only Sonne,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what to vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How came he to be ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was conceiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> After conception what followed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was <hi>borne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the virgin Marie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What was his entertainement in the world?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ſuffered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Vnder whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Poncious Pilate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kinde of death was he put vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was crucified.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:10"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Being on the Croſſe, did hee deliuer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: he <hi>dyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What was then done with him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He <hi>was buried.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what beleeue you concerning him, when his body was laid in the graue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he deſcended into Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Being in the graue did he lye there ſtill?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>he roſe againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The third day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> From whence?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What become of him after his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He aſcended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whither?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth he there?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There he ſitteth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> At the right hand of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> who is that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father Almighty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shall he abide there for euer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>from thence he ſhall come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What to doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To iudge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:10"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The quicke and the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In whom elſe doe you beleeue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> And what moreouer beleeue you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue that God hath a Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What a Church is this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Holy and Catholike.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What call you the fellowſhipe therein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Communion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what ſorts of perſons?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the ſpeciall prerogatiues to this Church, which no ſociety elſe partakes of, and which is the firſt of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The reſurrection of the body with ioy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How teſtifie you your aſſurance of theſe things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe you chiefly learne in theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of your beleife?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I learne thrée things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, I learne to beleeue in God the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What he hath done for you?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He hath made me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And whom elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And all the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond thing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Secondly, I beleeue in God the Sonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what hath he done for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hee hath redeemed me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And whom too?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And all mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third thing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thirdly, in God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth he for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He doth ſanctifie me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And whom beſides?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the elect people of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of the ten Commandements.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> YOu ſaid that your God-fathers and God-mothers did promiſe for you, that you ſhould keepe Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, tell me how many there be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Tenne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſame which God ſpake, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Are not theſe Commandements of man deuiſing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>they be the ſame which God ſpake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How proue you this?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the twentieth chapter of Exodus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What ſaith God there?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am the Lord thy God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom ſpake he vnto</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vnto all Iſraell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What had hee done for them, that hee calleth himſelfe their God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He brought them out of the Land of Aegypt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What was the Land vnto them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A houſe of bondage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is heare then forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To haue any other Gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is on the contrary commanded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To haue the God of Iſrael onely for our God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhall not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth this forbid?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To make to my ſelfe any grauen Image of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Is nothing elſe forbiden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes: <hi>the likeneſſe of any thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> May you no where fetch a ſimilitude to repreſent God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>not in heauen aboue, nor in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But what if any doe make ſuch grauen
<pb facs="tcp:19882:12"/> Image and likeneſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We may not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What reaſon is alledged?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For I am the Lord thy God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What a one is he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A iealous God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What will his iealouſie make him to doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To viſite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What will he viſite?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whoſe ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſinnes of the Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Vpon whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How farre?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To the third and fourth generation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What reckoning doth God make of theſe will-worſhippers?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As of them that hate him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But what will hee doe to them that deteſt idolatrie and vaine worſhip?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He will ſhew them mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How farre will he extend it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two thouſands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth he account of theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As of them that loue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And how is their loue to be knowne?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They keepe his Commandements.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:12"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is one the contrary here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?<note place="margin">Ioſ. 24. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ioh. 4. 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To worſhip God in ſpirit and truth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> What doth this forbid?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To take the name of our God in vaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By wicked ſwearing, and lewly liuing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What reaſon is their giuen to inforce this Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lords threatning, <hi>not to hold him guiltleſſe, that taken his name in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is heare on the contrary comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be carefull to doe and procure to God all due glory in thought, word, and deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the fourth Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Remember thou keepe holy the Sabbath day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is firſt here commanded you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To remember.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Sabbath day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Wherefore?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To keepe it holy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many dayes doth God allow vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it come?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sixe dayes,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are you to doe in theſe ſixe dayes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am to labour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In doing all that I haue to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why are you to labour thus ſixe dayes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For the ſeuenth day is the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whoſe Sabbath?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Sabbath of the Lord our God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is herein forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To doe in it any manner of worke</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who particularly by name are here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou, thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant, and thy maide ſeruant,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what elſe is forbidden labour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thy Cattell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And who beſides?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And the ſtranger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What ſtranger meane you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Which is within thy gates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What reaſon is giuen, for all this in the Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lords owne example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many dayes wrought he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sixe dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did he in thoſe ſixe dayes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He made the heauen, earth, and Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what elſe?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And all that in them is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did hee when the ſeuenth day came?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He reſted the ſeuenth day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did therefore the Lord vnto the ſeuenth day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Therefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He hallowed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fift commandement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Honour thy Father and thy Mother, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth this command?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Father and Mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What reaſon is alleaged to mooue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That thy dayes may be long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what Land?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here generally commanded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A preſeruation of dignitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is on the contrary forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All indignity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſixt Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here forbidden?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Murther,</hi>
                  </hi> and all hurt to my owne and Neighbours life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What on the contrary is here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Innocency.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſeuenth Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Adultery,</hi>
                  </hi> and all vncleanneſſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What on the contrary is here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Charitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the eight Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Theſe,</hi>
                  </hi> and all vniuſt dealing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is on the contrary commanded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Equitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ninth Commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Falſe witneſſe bearing,</hi>
                  </hi> and all vntruths.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Againſt whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Againſt my neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What on the contrary is commanded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Veritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the tenth Commandement?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not couet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here forbidden?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To couet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are you not to couet?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My neighbours houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nor his wife, nor his ſeruant, nor his maide, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beſides all theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nor any thing that is his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What on the contrary is here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Integritie</hi>
                  </hi> of heart, reſting thankefully contented euer with my preſent eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe you chiefly learne by theſe Commandements?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I learne two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My duty towards God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My duty towards my neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is your duty towards God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My duty towards God, is to beleeue in him, to feare him, and to loue him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are theſe words?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of the firſt Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here required of you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My dutie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Towards whom?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Towards God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many inward graces are required of you to doe your dutie to him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To beleeue in him, to feare him, and to loue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are youe to loue God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt loue him <hi>ſincerely, with all my heart,</hi> vnderſtandingly <hi>with all my minde,</hi> affectionately <hi>with all my ſoule,</hi> and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually <hi>with all my ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What will this make you doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To worſhip him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In receiuing of his benefits, what requires he of you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To giue him thankes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In all diſtreſſes, what is your dutie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To put my whole truſt in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What will this your truſt in diſtreſſe moue you vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To call vpon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is required generally of you what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer your eſtate be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To honour his holy name and his Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To manifeſt this, what muſt you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſerue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what manner?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Truly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How long?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the dayes of my life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is your dutie towards your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My dutie towards my neighbour is to loue him as my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are theſe words?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of the ſecond Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here required of you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My dutie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Towards my neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are you to doe to him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To loue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what manner?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As my owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What ought to be your generall carriage towards all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To doe to all men, as I would they ſhould doe vnto me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of all mankinde, whom in nature are you firſt to reſpect?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My Father and my Mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What owe you to them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Loue, honour and ſuccour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who are the next you are to haue regard of?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The King and his Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are you to doe to theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To honour and obey them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are you to carrie your ſelfe to them that haue command ouer you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt ſubmit my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To which of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <hi>all</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> How many ſorts are there of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Foure, Gouernours, Teachers, ſpirituall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, and Maſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What muſt be your commendable behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in generall to your betters?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To order my ſelfe lowly and reuerently to all my betters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are you to demeane your ſelfe, that you may liue harmeleſly to all ſorts?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To hurt nobody by word nor deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is required of you in your trading with men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be true and iuſt in all my dealings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What muſt your carriage be towards your enemies?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To beare them no malice nor hatred in my heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are you to keepe your hands from?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From picking and ſtealing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what your tongue from?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From al euil ſpeaking, lying, and, ſlandering</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:16"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are you to gouern your whole body?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To keep in temperance, ſoberneſſe, and chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may you attaine to liue contentedly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not to couet nor deſire other mens goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To affect this, what muſt you doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt learne and labour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> After what manner?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Truely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To what end?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To get my liuing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what too?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To doe my dutie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Wherein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In ſome ſtate of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What ſtate meane you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Euen that, vnto which it ſhall pleaſe God to call me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Queſtion before the Lords Prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> My good Child know this, that thou art not able to doe theſe things of thy ſelfe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To whom doth the Catechiſt ſpeake?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To me a child.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What a one accounteth he you to be, that thus can anſwere?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A good child.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What would he haue you to know?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Mine owne inabilitie, that <hi>I am not able
<pb facs="tcp:19882:17"/> to doe theſe things of my ſelfe, nor to walke in the commandements of God, and to ſerue him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Though you cannot of your ſelfe, is there therefore no helpe to make you able?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>the eſpeciall grace of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What muſt you doe to obtaine this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt learne at all times to call for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By diligent Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What forme of prayer haue you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which is called the Lords Prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> LEt mee heare therefore, can you ſay the Lords Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many parts are there in it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Three,</hi>
                  </hi> the Preface, the Petition, and the Concluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the Preface?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Father which art in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth this teach you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To whom onely I am to pray.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who is that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What call you him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whoſe Father is he?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom conceiue you in this word <hi>Our?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as haue the ſpirit of adoption, and are in the Communion of ſaints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where is this our Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many petitions be there?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sixe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hallowed be thy name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by name?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods titles, his properties, his word, and workes, by which hée is knowne, and<note place="margin">Exod. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> remembred as by a name, and ſo are a memoriall of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What vnderſtand you by <hi>hallowed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſetting apart of this name from all abuſe, to holy vſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What then begge you of God in this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That wee may remember ſo to doe, to thinke, &amp; ſpeake of God of his attributes, word, and works, as hee may receiue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glory, and praiſe by vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this petition in the firſt place?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Gods glory is to be firſt in all our deſires and purpoſes,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thy Kingdome come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:18"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by his kingdome?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The rule of God in our hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> How muſt this be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By his word and ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What aske you hearein of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God would here ſubdue the Deuill, the World, and the fleſh, and graciouſly ſubiect vs to his will by his word and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we may come to heauen in the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this petition ſet after the former?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For that this is the meanes to hallow his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thy will bee done in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by his <hi>will?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods will reuealed in his written word, the onely rule of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire you of God herein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That wée may haue grace to leaue our owne wils, and to doe his will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here in earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But after what manner?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Euen <hi>as it is in heauen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 119. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3. 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is that?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Willingly, readily, ioyfully, faithfully, ſincerely and conſtantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this petition the next after the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe this ſheweth the true effect of the former, that indéed Gods kingdome of grace is come vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fourth Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by <hi>bread?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All things neceſſary for vs in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What begge you of God herein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God would ſuſtaine our liues here with all temporall neceſſaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How aske you for theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As Gods owne gift.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For whom aske you theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> my ſelfe, and all Gods people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what time?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For <hi>this day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whoſe bread aske you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Our</hi>
                  </hi> owne, gotten by lawfull meanes, through Gods bleſſing in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What manner of bread aske you for?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Daily bread,</hi>
                  </hi> that which is agréeable to nature, and conuenient for our calling and charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this next the other Petition?</p>
               <p>A. Becauſe ſupply of bodily neceſſaries, ſhould make vs more chéerefull to doe Gods will.</p>
               <p>Q. Which is the fift Petition?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by <hi>treſpaſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our ſinns.<note place="margin">Luk. 11. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> And what by <hi>forgiueneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The not imputing ſinne vnto vs, and fully acquiting vs through Chriſt, both<note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 12</note> from the guilt and puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What then begge you of God in this Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God would in mercie pardon and forgiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi>
                  </hi> I and all other his children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our treſpaſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Petition next after the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That wee may not forget in the midſt of temporall bleſſings to ſéeke reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to be at peace with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the reaſon added to the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is your duty, when you aske for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To forgiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who are to forgiue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>Wee,</hi>
                  </hi> I and all, that aske forgiueneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom are you to forgiue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Them that treſpaſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Againſt whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Againſt <hi>vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Is your forgiuing like vnto Gods, and a cauſe thereof?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this then added to the Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As a ſigne, aſſuring vs of our forgiueneſſe<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 14. 15.</note> grounded vpon Chriſts promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſixt Petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And leade vs not into temptation, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vs from euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by <hi>temptation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icement vnto ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by leading into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be left of God in the time of triall to my ſelfe, and to the power of the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What begge you of God in this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not to be forſaken of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the time of temptation and triall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What would you haue him then to doe for vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To deliuer vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> From what?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From <hi>the euill</hi> of the temptation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Petition added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For that wee, which craue the aſſurance of pardon for ſinnes paſt, are alſo to begge aſſiſtance of Gods grace to preuent ſinne to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the Concluſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For thine is the Kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What containe theſe words?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A reaſon of aſſurance in our praying to God, for ſuch things as bee contained in the petitions.<note place="margin">Ch. 29. 11. Ch. 20. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b 41. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 42. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 115. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 34. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o 23. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke 1. 37. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 19. 26 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hr. 20. 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u. 19. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 11. 36 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 5. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 4. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 1. 17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. 4. 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 13. 15</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many things are here aſcribed to God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thrée.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>The Kingdome,</hi>
                  </hi> his abſolut rule ouer all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>The power,</hi>
                  </hi> ſo infinite, as he is able to doe what hee pleaſeth, being the Lord God omnipotent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is third?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. <hi>The glory,</hi>
                  </hi> for to him, prayſe, honour, and thankes are due for all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How long are theſe his?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are theſe ſaid to be his?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Originally, Abſolutely, and Eternally.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 1 Reu. 1. 6. Pro. 8. 15 Rom. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iob. 33. 13 1 Tim. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ier. 11. 5. Num. 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deut. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mat. 28. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the laſt word after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this added in the end?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To teſtifie my deſire, to haue that I aske, ſaying, <hi>ſo be it:</hi> as alſo to ſhew my faith, that <hi>ſo it ſhall be,</hi> as I haue asked, if God thinke it good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire you of God in this prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I deſire my Lord God our heauenly Father who is the giuer of all goodneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are theſe words?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſhort ſumme of things which I beg of God in prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who is to pray?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> My ſelfe as well as others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What affection are you to pray with?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With <hi>deſire</hi> to haue my requeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whom are you to pray vnto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To my Lord God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who is he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our heauenly Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What moueth you to pray to him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is the giuer of all goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What chiefly in the firſt place doe you begge of him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſend his grace vnto me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To whom elſe?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And to all people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why deſire you this grace for you and them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we may worſhip him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When doe we worſhip him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we <hi>ſerue him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And when ſerue we him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we <hi>obey him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What elſe pray you for beſides?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he will ſend vs all things that be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For our ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what next?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. And for our bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When God ſends you his grace and all theſe neceſſaries, what more neede you to begge of him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he will be mercifull to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you ſpecially by this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To forgiue vs our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That it would pleaſe him to ſaue and defend vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In all dangers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what kinde of danger?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ghoſtly and bodyly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What moreouer pray you for?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he will keepe vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> From what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From all ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And from what elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And from our Ghoſtly enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the laſt danger you deſire to bee kept from?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kinde of death?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Euerlaſting death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What perſwaſion haue you in thus making your requeſt vnto God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This I truſt he will doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Vpon what ground do you thus truſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of his mercie and goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By whoſe meanes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Through our Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who is he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What conclude you hereupon?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Therefore I ſay, Amen,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by <hi>Amen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of the Sacraments.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> HOw many Sacraments hath Chriſt ordained in his Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two <hi>generally neceſſarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:22"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by this word <hi>Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I meane a ſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kind of ſigne?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Outward and viſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Inward and ſpirituall grace,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> To whom is it giuen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Giuen vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By whom was it ordained?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ordained by Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For what end?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, <hi>as a meanes whereby wee receiue the ſame grace,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And why elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Secondly, <hi>to bee as a pleadge to aſſure vs thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many parts be their in a <hi>Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The outwiad viſible ſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The inward ſpirituall grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of Batiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> VVHat is the outward viſible ſigne in Baptiſme?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is done with it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With it the perſon Baptiſed is dipped or ſprinkled.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is it adminiſtred?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the inward and ſpirituall grace?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The purging of our ſoules by the blood of Chriſt, and ſanctification of the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the firſt effect hereof?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A death vnto ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A new birth vnto righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why ſpeake you thus of a death vnto ſinne, and a new birth vnto righteouſneſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For that by nature we are borne in ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are we in this naturall eſtate?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Children of wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what are wee being thus renewed in Baptiſme?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are hereby made the children of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is required of perſons baptized?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the power thereof?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That thereby we forſake ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the ſecond?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the efficacy and force thereof?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> That whereby we beleeue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How muſt you beleeue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Stedfaſtly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What muſt you beleeue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The promiſes of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Made to whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Made to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that Sacrament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why then are infants baptiſed when by reaſon of their tender age they cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They doe performe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By their ſuerties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What haue they done for them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They promiſed and vowed them both in their names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Is this enough for thoſe Infants if they liue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>but when they come to age, themſelues are bound to performe them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <head>Of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> WHy was the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ordained?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For a remembrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kinde of remembrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A continuall remembrance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:23"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the ſacrifice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And of what elſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And of the benefits which wee receiue thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the outward part or ſigne of the Lords ſupper?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By what warrant are theſe both to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>the Lord hath commanded them to be receiued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the inward part or thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are theſe receiued?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are verily and in deede taken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the benefits whereof wee are made partakers thereby?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of ſtrengthening and refreſhing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> By what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the body and blood of Chriſt</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:24"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is the reſemblance expreſſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As our bodies are by the bread and wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is required of them which come to the Lords ſupper?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To examine themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Whether they repent them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Truly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of their former ſinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may their truly repenting appeare?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By ſteadfaſtly purpoſing to lead a new life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What elſe muſt they haue with it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They muſt haue faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kind of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A liuely faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Gods mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Through whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Through Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What more muſt you come with?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With a remembrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What kinde of remembrance?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With a thankefull remembrance,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of what?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And how laſtly muſt you come?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In charity.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19882:24"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q.</hi> With whom are you to bee in Charity?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What if you come vnprepared without theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I come vnworthy, I eate and drinke my owne damnation. God may puniſh me, and the Deuill may enter into me, as he did in <hi>Iudas,</hi> and bring me to deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of body and ſoule: from which euils the Lord deliuer vs, for his mercie ſake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
